Where are you? Come out!
Come out!
Come on out.
I'm coming to get you.
Where are you, you little rascal?
Where is my little birthday girl?
I'm going to gobble her
up when I find her.
I'm going to eat you. I am.
Fergus, no weapons on the table.
Can I shoot an arrow? Can I?
Can I? Can I? Can I?
Please? Can I?
Not with that. Why not
use your very own?
Happy birthday, my wee darling!
Now, there's a good girl.
Draw all the way back now to your cheek.
That's right.
Keep both eyes open.
And, loose!
- I missed
- Go and fetch it, then.
A bow, Fergus? She's a lady.
You!
A will-o'-the-wisp.
They are real.
Merida, come along, sweetheart.
- We're leaving now.
- I saw a wisp.
- A wisp?
You know, some say that will-o'-the-wisps
lead you to your fate.
Aye. Or an arrow.
Come on, let's be off before
we see a dancing Tatty Bogle.
Or a giant having a
jigger in the bluebells.
Your father doesn't believe in magic.
Well, he should. Because it's true.
Mor'du! Elinor, run!
Sire!
Come on, you!
Some say our destiny
is tied to the land
as much a pan' of us as we are of it.
Others say fate is woven
together like a cloth.
So that one's destiny
intertwines with many others.
It's the one thing we search
for or fight to change.
Some never find it.
But there are some who are led.
The story of how my father lost his leg
to the demon bear
Mor'du became legend.
I became a sister to
three new brothers.
The princes. Hamish,
Hubert and Harris.
Wee devils, more like.
They get away with murder.
I can never get away with anything.
I'm the princess.
I'm the example.
I've got duties,
responsibilities, expectations.
My whole life is planned out,
preparing for the day I become...
Well, my mother.
She's in charge of every
single day of my life.
"Aye, Robin, Jolly Robin, and
thou shalt know of mine."
Project!
"And thou shalt know of mine!"
Enunciate. You must be understood
from anywhere in the room,
or it's all for naught.
- This is all for naught.
- I heard that!
From the top.
A princess must be knowledgeable
about her kingdom.
She does not doodle.
That's a C, dear.
A princess does not chortle.
Does not stuff her gob!
Rises early.
...Is compassionate...
...patient, cautious,
clean.
And above all, a princess strives for...
Well, perfection.
But every once in a while,
there's a day when I don't
have to be a princess.
No lessons, no expectations.
A day where anything can happen.
A day I can change my fate.
I'm starving. You hungry too, Angus?
Oats it is, then.
Good day, Princess.
I cannot find the salt.
Where did you put it?
It was over there a minute ago,
the last time I looked at it.
And then, out of nowhere, the
biggest bear you've ever seen!
His hide littered with the
weapons of fallen warriors.
His face scarred with one dead eye.
I drew my sword and...
One swipe, his sword shattered.
Then "chomp"! Dad's leg was clean off.
Down the monster's throat it went.
That's my favorite part.
Mor'du has never been seen since,
and is roaming the wilds
waiting his chance of revenge.
Let him return.
I'll finish what I guddled
in the first place.
Merida, a princess does not
place her weapons on the table.
Mum! It's just my bow.
A princess should not have
weapons in my opinion.
Leave her be.
Princess or not, learning
to fight is essential.
Mum? You'll never guess
what I did today.
I climbed the Crone's Tooth,
and drank from the Fire Falls.
Fire Falls?
They say only the ancient kings were
brave enough to drink the fire.
- What did you do, dear?
- Nothing, Mum.
Hungry, aren't we?
- Mum!
- You'll get dreadful collywobbles.
Oh, Fergus, will you look
at your daughter's plate?
So what?
- You great...
- Don't let them lick...
Boys, you're naughty.
Don't just play with your haggis.
How do you know you don't like it,
if you won't try it?
That's just a wee sheep's stomach.
It's delicious.
- My lady.
- Thank you, Maudie.
You're getting too big, the two of you.
From the Lords Macintosh,
MacGuffin and Dingwall.
Their responses, no doubt.
Aye, aye!
Hey, hey!
Stay out of my food,
you greedy mongrels.
Chew on that, you manky dogs!
Fergus?
They've all accepted.
Who's accepted what, Mother?
Boys, you are excused.
Hey!
What did I do now?
Your father has something
to discuss with you.
Fergus?
Merida.
The lords are presenting their sons
as suitors for your betrothal.
- What?
- The clans have accepted.
- Dad!
- What? I...
You... She... Elinor?
Honestly, Merida, I don't know
why you're reacting this way.
This year, each clan
will present a suitor
to compete in the games for your hand.
I suppose a princess just
does what she's told?
A princess does not raise her voice.
Merida, this is what you've been
preparing for your whole life.
No, it's what you've been
preparing me for my whole life.
I won't go through with it.
You can't make me.
Merida!
Boys!
Mother. Suitors? Marriage?
Once there was an ancient kingdom...
Mum!
Ancient kingdom.
Its name long forgotten,
ruled by a wise and fair
king who was much beloved.
And when he grew old he divided
the kingdom among his four sons,
that they should be the pillars on
which the peace of the land rested.
But the oldest prince wanted
to rule the land for himself.
He followed his own path
and the kingdom fell
to war, and chaos and ruin.
That's a nice story.
It's not just a story, Merida.
Legends are lessons.
They ring with truths.
Mum.
I would advise you to make
your peace with this.
The clans are coming to
present their suitors.
- It's not fair.- Merida.
It's marriage. It's not
the end of the world.
- You're muttering.
- I don't mutter.
Aye, you do. You mutter, lass,
when something's troubling you.
I blame you. Stubbornness.
It's entirely from your side of the family.
I take it the talk didn't
go too well, then?
I don't know what to do.
- Speak to her, dear.
- I do speak to her.
- She just doesn't listen.
- Come on, now.
Pretend I'm Merida. Speak to me.
What would you say?
I can't do this.
Sure you can.
There, there. That's my queen.
Right, here we go.
"I don't want to get married."
"I want to stay single and
let my hair flow in the wind"
"as I ride through the glen
firing arrows into the sunset."
Merida, all this work, all the
time spent preparing you,
schooling you, giving you
everything we never had.
I ask you, what do you expect us to do?
Call off the gathering.
Would that kill them?
You're the queen.
You can just tell the lords the
princess is not ready for this.
In fact, she might not ever be
ready for this, so that's that.
Good day to you. We'll expect your
declarations of war in the morning.
I understand this must all seem unfair.
Even I had reservations
when I faced betrothal.
But we can't just run
away from who we are.
I don't want my life to be over.
I want my freedom!
But are you willing to pay the
price your freedom will cost?
I'm not doing any of this to hurt you.
If you could just try to see
what I do, I do out of love.
But it's my life, it's...
I'm just not ready.
I think you'd see, if you could just...
I think I could make you
understand if you would just...
...listen.
- ...listen.
I swear, Angus, this
isn't going to happen.
Not if I have any say in it.
MacGuffin!
- Dingwall!
- Macintosh!
You look absolutely beautiful.
I can't breathe.
Shush! Give us a turn.
I can't move.
It's too tight.
It's perfect.
- Merida?
- Mum?
Just...
Remember to smile.
Aye, they're coming.
Places, everyone. Places.
I look fine, woman! Leave me be!
My Lord!
I want to announce the
arrival of the lords...
Who goes there? Who goes there?
Boy!
So, here we are,
the four clans.- Aye.
Gathering...
...for...
...the presentation of the suitors.
- ...the presentation of the suitors.
Clan Macintosh.
Macintosh!
Your Majesty, I present
my heir and scion,
who defended our land from
the northern invaders,
and with his own sword, Stab Blooder,
vanquished 1,000 foes.
Macintosh!
Clan MacGuffin!
MacGuffin!
Good Majesty, I present my eldest son,
who scuttled the Viking longships
and with his bare hands
vanquished 2,000 foes.
MacGuffin!
Clan Dingwall.
Dingwall!
I present my only son
who was besieged by 10,000 Romans
and he took out a whole
armada singlehandedly.
With one arm, he was...
With one arm he was steering the ship
and with the other he
held his mighty sword
and struck down a whole attacking fleet.
- Lies!- What? I heard that.
Go on. Say it to my face.
Or are ye scared,
simpering jackanapes,
afraid to muss your pretty hair?
- At least we have hair.
- And all our teeth.
If he was a wee bit closer...
And we don't hide under
bridges, you grumpy old troll.
You want to laugh, huh?
Wee Dingwall!
Get off me!
Nut 'em! Nut 'em! That's the way to...
All right.
Shut it!
Now, that's all done. You've
had your go at each other.
Show a little decorum.
And no more fighting.
You want a fresh one?
Crivens, you're fierce.
I didn't start it. It was...
My lady Queen, I feel terrible.
My humblest apologies.
- We mean no disrespect.
- I'm sorry, love, I didn't... But...
Yes, dear.
Now, where were we?
Yes. In accordance with our laws,
by the rights of our heritage,
only the firstborn of
each of the great leaders
may be presented as champion.
- Firstborn?
And thus compete for the hand
of the Princess of Dun Broch.
To win the fair maiden they
must prove their worth
by feats of strength
or arms in the games.
It is customary that the challenge be
determined by the princess herself.
Archery! Archery.
I choose archery.
Let the games begin!
Pull!
I'll just take one.
Now, I have told you,
you're not allowed...
It's time!
- Archers, to your marks!
- Aye, archers to your marks.
And may the lucky arrow find its target.
Oi! Get on with it.
I bet he wishes he was tossing cabers.
Or holding up bridges.
At least you hit the target, son.
That's attractive.
- I got it!- Good arm.
And such lovely flowing locks.
- Fergus.- What?
Wee lamb.
Come on! Shoot, boy!
Well done, lad! Well done.
Feast your eyes!
That's my boy.
Well, that's just grand now, isn't it?
- Guess who's coming to dinner?
- Fergus.
By the way, hope you don't
mind being called Lady...
I am Merida.
Firstborn descendant
of Clan Dun Broch.
And I'll be shooting for my own hand.
What are you doing?
Merida!
Curse this dress!
Merida, stop this!
Don't you dare loose another arrow.
Merida, I forbid it.
Michty me!
I've just about had enough of you, lass!
- You're the one that wants me to...
- You embarrassed them.
- You embarrassed me.
- I followed the rules.
You don't know what you've done!
- Just don't care how I...
- It'll be fire and sword if it's not set right.
- Just listen!
- I am the Queen!
You listen to me!
This is so unfair!
Unfair?
You're never there for me.
This whole marriage is what you want.
Do you ever bother to
ask what I want? No.
You walk around telling me
what to do, what not to do,
trying to make me be like you.
Well, I'm not going to be like you.
You're acting like a child.
And you're a beast.
- That's what you are!
- Merida.
- I'll never be like you.
- No, stop that!
I'd rather die than be like you!
Merida, you are a princess,
and I expect you to act like one.
- Mum!
Merida!
Oh, dear.
Oh, no. What have I done?
Angus!
Come on, Angus.
Why would the wisps lead me here?
Look around.
You holler if you see anything you like.
Everything is half off.
- Who are you?
- Just a humble woodcarver.
I don't understand...
See anything you like?
Perhaps a touch of whimsy to
brighten any dank chamber?
But the will-o'-the-wisps, they...
This is one of a kind!
I'll make you a deal for this rare prize.
Your broom!
- It was sweeping by itself.
- That's ridiculous.
Wood cannot be imbued
with magical properties.
I should know. I'm a... Whittler.
Of wood.
How about this conversation starter?
It's made of yew wood.
Tough as stone.
That's stuffed.
- Staring is rude.
- The crow's talking!
That's not all I can do.
- You're a witch!
- Woodcarver.
That's why the wisps led me here.
- Woodcarver!
- You'll change my fate!
- You see, it's my mother.
I'm not a witch! Too many
unsatisfied customers.
If you're not going to
buy anything, get out.
- No! The wisps led me here!
- I don't care!
- Get out! Shoo! Get! Be gone with you!
- I'll buy it all.
- What? What was that?
- Every carving.
Well...
And how are you going to
pay for that, sweetie?
With this.
Oh, my, that's lovely, that is.
That would set us up for months.
Every carving and one spell.
Are you sure you know
what you're doing?
I want a spell to change my mum.
That'll change my fate.
Done!
Where are you going?
There.
What are you doing?
You never conjure where you carve.
Very important.
The last time I did
this was for a prince.
Easy on the eyes. Tight pants.
He demanded I give him
the strength of ten men.
And he gave me this for a spell.
A spell that would change his fate.
And did he get what he was after?
Yes. And made off with an especially
attractive mahogany cheese board.
Now, what do I need?
Just a little bit of this.
That'll do.
And now let's see. What have we here?
Hey!
A cake?
- You don't want it?
- Yes! I want it.
You're sure if I give this to my mum,
it will change my fate?
Trust me. It'll do the trick, dearie.
Expect delivery of your
purchase within a fortnight.
What was that thing about the spell?
Did you say something about
the spell?
Mor'du, Mor'du, now the time has
come for all of us to slaughter you
Hooray!
Mor'du, Mor'du...
- Merida.
- Mum!
- I've been worried sick.
- You... You were?
I didn't know where you'd
gone or when you'd come back.
I didn't know what to think.
Look at your dress.
Angus threw me. But I'm not hurt.
Well, you're home now,
so that's the end of it.
- Honestly?
- I've pacified the lords for now.
Your father's out there
"entertaining" them.
Come taste my blade, you manky bear
For gobbling up my leg
I'll hunt you, then I'll skin
you, hang your noggin on a peg...
Of course, we both know a
decision still has to be made.
- What's this?
- It's a peace offering.
I made it. For you. Special.
You made this for me?
Interesting flavor.
How do you feel?
- What... What is that?
- Different?
Tart and gamy.
Have you changed your mind at all
about the marriage and all that?
That's better.
Now, why don't we go
upstairs to the lords
and put this whole kerfuffle to rest?
- Mother?
- I'm woozy suddenly.
My head's spinning like a top.
- Mum!
- Suddenly I'm not so well.
How do you feel about
the marriage now?
Merida! Just take me to my room.
All right, that's fine.
That's just fine.
A little to the left. That's good. A
wee bit to the left. That's good.
It's good enough.
Now, clear out of there, boys. I
don't want you to spoil my shot.
- What?
- My lady Queen.
We've been waiting patiently.
Milords, I am out of
sorts at the moment.
But you shall have your answer.
Presently.
Now, if you'll excuse us.
Elinor, look!
It's Mor'du!
Elinor? Are you all right, dear?
Fine. I'm fine.
Go about avenging your leg.
Aye. You heard her, lads.
I dream about the perfect
way to make this devil die.
Just take all the time you need
to getting yourself right, Mum.
Then maybe in a bit you might have
something new to say on the marriage.
What was in that cake?
Cake.
Mum?
So I'll just tell them
the wedding's off, then?
Mum?
Bear!
You're... You're a bear!
Why a bear?
That scaffy witch gave
me a gammy spell.
It's not my fault.
I didn't ask her to
change you into a bear.
I just wanted her to change you.
Did you hear that?
Something's not right.
There's no point in having a go at me.
The witch is to blame.
Goggly old hag.
Eyes all over the place.
Unbelievable.
I'll get her to fix this.
Why do I always get blamed for everything?
It's just not fair.
Everybody, follow me.
And keep a sharp eye.
Here we go. Another hunt
through the castle.
But we haven't had dessert yet.
I have no idea.
Mum, you can't go out there.
Mum! Wait!
What are you doing? Dad.
The Bear King?
If he so much as sees you, you're dead.
Another one of your entertainments
to bore us to death!
And what exactly are we after...
Mum!
...my liege?
Best to humor him. He is,
after all, the King.
He's like a hound with that nose of his.
Mum, wait.
We have to...
Follow me.
Stop.
Stop!
You're covered with fur.
You're not naked.
It's not like anyone's gonna see you.
Now you've done it.
Maudie!
Just calm down, lass. What is it?
Spit it out, Maudie!
A bear!
I knew it!
Would you just listen to me?
We can't go this way. You'll be seen.
Quick! This way!
Mum?
A witch turned Mum into a bear.
It's not my fault.
We've got to get out of the castle.
I need your help.
All right.
You can have my desserts for two...
Three weeks.
Okay. Fine. A year.
Did you hear that?
There it goes!
Come on, lads!
Come on, Mum.
Think we should lay a trap?
Try shutting yours!
There he is!
I'm sure it went this way.
You can see my house from here.
It must have sprouted wings.
Was carried away by a giant birdy.
- A dragon, perhaps.
- Bear in the castle!
Doesn't make sense.
It cannot open doors.
He's got big giant paws!
Let's just get inside.
- It's locked.
- Dingwall was the last up.
I propped it open with a stick.
What did you see, Maudie?
Just spit it out, Maudie.
For goodness' sakes, Maudie,
would you get a grip?
Maudie, honey, come here!
It's all right!
Come on, Mum. Quick.
They'll be fine. Won't you, boys?
Mum, we've got to hurry.
Now, I'll be back soon.
Go on and help yourself to
anything you want, as a reward.
Right!
Where are these wisps?
Come out, wisps. Come on out.
Lead me to the witch's cottage.
I'm here!
Fine. Don't come out now
that my mum's watching.
I was standing right here and
the wisp appeared right there.
Then a whole trail of them
led me off into the forest.
Does she think we're just going to
happen upon the witch's cottage?
Mum, I know this place.
The witch's cottage...
It's this way! Come on! Hurry!
I can't believe it. I found it.
No. She was here.
No, really, she was just here.
Wait.
No.
No, no. No! No!
Welcome to the Crafty Carver,
home of bear-themed
carvings and novelties.
I am completely out of
stock at this time.
But if you'd like to enquire about
portraits or wedding cake toppers,
pour vial one into the cauldron.
If you'd like the menu
in Gaelic, vial two.
If you're that red-haired lass, vial three.
To speak with a live homunculus...
Princess, I'm off to the Wickerman
Festival in Stornoway
and won't be back till spring.
There's one bit I forgot to
tell you about the spell.
By the second sunrise, your
spell will be permanent,
unless you remember these words.
Fate be changed,
look inside,
mend the bond
torn by pride.
"Fate be changed... Mend the bond.
" What does that mean?
One more time.
Fate be changed,
look inside,
mend the bond
torn by pride.
That's it. Ta-ta.
And thank you for shopping
at the Crafty Carver.
No. No! Where'd you go?
- Welcome to the Crafty Carver...
- What?
...for all your...
Maybe there's a book of spells. Look around.
We'll need more vials.
I'm off to the Wickerman Festival
in Stornoway...
Thank you for visiting.
Have a lovely day.
We'll sort it out tomorrow.
My brave wee lassie, I'm here.
I'll always be right here.
Good morning.
So...
What's all this supposed to be?
What?
Sorry. I don't speak bear.
Find those by the creek, did you?
They're nightshade berries.
They're poisonous.
Where did you get this water?
It has worms.
Come on.
Breakfast.
Wait. A princess should not
have weapons, in your opinion.
There you go.
Go on.
How do you know you don't
like it if you won't try it?
Hey!
Where are you going?
Mum, come back.
Mum, is that you?
Mum?
You changed.
Like you were a...
I mean, like you were
a bear on the inside.
A wisp.
Mum!
Stop it!
Mum, no!
Mum...
Jings, crivens, help ma boab.
Mum, I know you're scared,
you're tired, you don't understand,
but we've got to keep our heads.
Just calm down.
Listen.
They'll show us the way.
Mum, look.
Why did the wisps bring us here?
Whoever they were, they've been
gone for a long, long time.
I'm fine, Mum. Just fine.
It's
a throne room.
You suppose this could've
been the kingdom
in that story you were telling me?
The one with the princes.
One,
two,
three,
four.
The oldest.
Split, like the tapestry.
The spell. It's happened before.
"Strength of ten men."
"Fate be changed."
"Changed his fate."
Oh, no.
The prince became...
Mor'du.
Mum, we need to get back to the castle.
If we don't hurry, you'll
become like Mor'du.
A bear!
A real bear. Forever!
"Mend the bond torn by pride."
The witch gave us the answer.
The tapestry.
Mum, do you have a better idea?
That'll do.
No more talk.
No more traditions. We settle this now!
You're the King.
You decide which one of our
sons your daughter will marry.
None of your sons are fit
to marry my daughter.
Then our alliance is over!
This means war!
They're gonna murder each other.
You've got to stop them
before it's too late.
I know, I know!
But how do we get you through
there and up to the tapestry
with the lot of them
boiling over like that?
- What are you doing, lass?
- It's all right, Dad.
I...
I have...
Well, you see, I...
I have been in conference
with the Queen.
- Is that so?
- Aye, it is.
- Well, where is she, then?
- She...
How do we know that
this isn't some trick?
- I'd never...
- This is highly irregular.
- What are you playing at?
- Where is the Queen?
We will not stand for any
more of this jiggery-pokery.
- That's right. Let's see her.
- Shut it!
Well, I...
Once there was an ancient kingdom.
What is this?
That kingdom fell into war
and chaos and ruin...
We've all heard that tale.
Lost kingdom.
Aye, but it's true.
I know now how one selfish act
can turn the fate of a kingdom.
It's just a legend.
Legends are lessons.
They ring with truths.
Our kingdom is young.
Our stories are not yet legend.
But in them, our bond was struck.
Our clans were once enemies.
But when invaders
threatened us from the sea,
you joined together to defend our lands.
You fought for each other.
You risked everything for each other.
Lord MacGuffin, my dad saved your life,
stopping an arrow as you
ran to Dingwall's aid.
Aye, and I'll never forget it.
And, Lord Macintosh,
you saved my dad when you
charged in on heavy horse
and held off the advance.
And we all know how Lord
Dingwall broke the enemy line.
With a mighty throw of his spear!
I was aiming at you, you big tumshie.
The story of this kingdom
is a powerful one.
My dad rallied your forces
and you made him your king.
It was an alliance forged
in bravery and friendship
and it lives to this day.
But I've been selfish.
I tore a great rift in our kingdom.
There's no one to blame but me.
And I know now that I
need to amend my mistake
and mend our bond.
And so, there is the
matter of my betrothal.
I've decided to do what's right
and...
...and...
...break tradition.
My mother,
the Queen, feels...
in her heart
that I...
...that we be free to...
...write our own story...
...follow our hearts
and find love in our own time.
That's beautiful.
The Queen and I put the
decision to you, my lords.
Might our young people decide for
themselves who they will love?
Well, since you've obviously
made up your minds about this,
I have one thing to say.
- This is...
- A grand idea!
Give us our own say
in choosing our fate.
- What?
- Aye. Why shouldn't we choose?
But she's the princess.
I did not pick her out. It was your idea.
And you... You feel the same way?
Good?
Well, that settles it.
Let these lads try and win her
heart before they win her hand.
If they can.
I say, the wee Dingwall
has a fighting chance.
Fine, then. Seems for once we agree.
It was my idea in the first place.
Just like your mum.
You devil.
Everyone to the cellar!
Let's crack open the King's
private reserve to celebrate!
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Bring the tiny glasses.
Oh, the tapestry!
Mend the bond...
Mend the bond.
Stitch it up. This'll change you back.
We just need needle and thread.
Mum?
Mum? Not now.
No. Please, not now.
Mum...
Elinor, clear, you'll never guess who
just solved our little suitor problem.
Elinor!
It can't be true! Elinor,
answer me, lass!
Elinor!
Merida.
- What?
- Dad, no! It's not what you think.
- Merida, get back!- No!
No, Dad! Don't hurt her!
Get out of here!
Merida! No!
No!
Mum.
It's all right. I'm all right. It's nothing.
It's just a little scratch. Mum!
My liege!
Fergus.
Bear!
Dad!
Count your stars, lass. It almost had you.
Are you hurt?
It's your wife, Elinor.
Close the gate!
- You're talking nonsense!
- It's the truth!
There was a witch and she gave me a spell.
It's not Mor'du.
Mor'du or not, I'll avenge your mother!
- I'll not risk losing you, too.
- No, Dad! Just listen to me.
Listen! You can't!
- It's your wife Elinor!
- Maudie, keep this and don't let her out.
- What about the bear?
- Just stay put.
Come on, you sorry bunch of galoots!
Mum!
No.
No. Mum.
Maudie. Maudie!
I need you!
Now!
Oh, no.
Maudie.
Get the key.
Maudie!
Needle and thread. Needle and thread.
Needle and thread.
There he goes!
Needle and thread. Needle and thread.
Needle and thread.
You beauty!
One, two...
Steady, Hamish.
There he goes.
We've got his track!
- Back, back, back!
- Get him!
Angus! Easy, laddie.
Hubert, Harris, help Hamish.
Watch your blade! You're going
to take somebody's arm off!
Aye, we've got you now!
- Give me a hand over here!
- Put your back into it, Dingwall!
I'm doing all the pulling here.
Down you go, you scoundrel.
Done!
- Get back. That's my mother.
- Are you out of your mind, lass?
Mum, are you hurt?
Merida!
I'll not let you kill my mother.
Boys!
Boys?
- Mor'du!
- Kill it!
You Scoundrel!
Come on! I'll take you
with my bare hands!
Mum!
The second sunrise.
No...
I don't understand. I...
Oh, Mum, I'm sorry.
This is all my fault.
I did this to you.
To us.
You've always been there for me.
You've never given up on me.
I just want you back.
I want you back, Mummy.
I love you.
Mum! You're back!
You changed!
Oh, darling,
we both have.
Elinor!
Oh, dear.
You're back. She came back to us.
It's a great day for this kingdom.
The curse is broke.
Mum.
Dear?
I'm naked.
Naked as a wee babby.
Don't just stare at me. Do something!
What the... Avert your eyes, lads!
Show some respect!
Now that's what I call
a wee naked babby!
Merida, Elinor, hurry up.
They're leaving.
- Mum!
- They're off! Come on!
We've got to wave them off!
Come along!
Goodbye! All the best!
Fair wind to your sails!
But how did this...
There are those who say fate is
something beyond our command,
that destiny is not our own.
But I know better.
Our fate lives within us.
You only have to be
brave enough to see it.
Delivery. Sign here, sign here.
Come on, birdbrain. I
haven't got all day.